Guide to the Polly Scribner Ames Papers 1938-1993
University of Chicago Library
Ames, Polly Scribner. Papers
1938-1993
8.75 linear feet (17 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
Polly Scribner Ames (1908-1993) was a painter, sculptor, and writer who lived in Chicago, New York, and Europe. The Polly Scribner Ames papers contain manuscripts, correspondence, journals, and records of exhibitions and sales of artwork.
Information on Use
Access
The collection is open for research.
Biographical Note
Polly Scribner Ames was the daughter of University of Chicago philosophy professor and University Church pastor Edward Scribner Ames and the sister of Van Meter Ames, University of Cincinnati philosophy professor and author. Born in 1908, Ames attended the School of the Art Institute Chicago and received a Ph.B. from the University of Chicago. She lived in New York City for much of her adult life and also spent time in Europe, including several years in France. She exhibited paintings and sculpture and taught art courses in both the United States and Europe. Ames died in Chicago in 1993.
Scope Note
Series I contains drafts of published and unpublished manuscripts, including a memoir, short stories, nonfiction articles, and poetry. Correspondence concerning the publication of Ames’s book about the painter Marsden Hartley is also included in this series. Some manuscripts by others are contained in this series, as well as publicity for and reviews of exhibitions of Ames’s painting and sculpture. Series II contains correspondence among various members of the Ames family, as well as Polly Scribner Ames’s other personal and professional correspondence. Also included are Ames’s journals, the bulk of which are from the 1960s. Series III contains several oversize items, including exhibition advertisements and press clippings as well as research for Ames’s book about Marsden Hartley.
The contents of Box 12A were previously part of the Miscellaneous Manuscripts Collection.
Related Resources
Browse finding aids by topic.
Subject Headings
Ames, Polly Scribner, 1908-; Ames, Edward Scribner, 1870-1958; Art, American; Women artists; Women sculptors; Women authors
INVENTORY
- Series I: Writing and Artwork
  - A Chance of My Making, manuscript draft (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - A Chance of My Making, manuscript draft (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - A Chance of My Making, manuscript draft (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - A Chance of My Making, manuscript draft (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - A Chance of My Making, manuscript draft (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - A Chance of My Making, manuscript draft (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - A Chance of My Making, manuscript draft (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - A Chance of My Making, manuscript draft (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - A Chance of My Making, manuscript draft (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - A Chance of My Making, manuscript draft (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - A Chance of My Making, manuscript draft (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - A Chance of My Making, manuscript draft (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - A Chance of My Making, manuscript draft (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - A Chance of My Making, manuscript draft (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - A Chance of My Making, manuscript draft (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - A Chance of My Making, manuscript draft (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - A Chance of My Making, manuscript draft (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - A Chance of My Making, manuscript draft (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - A Chance of My Making, manuscript draft (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - A Chance of My Making, manuscript draft (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - A Chance of My Making, manuscript draft (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - A Chance of My Making, manuscript draft (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - A Chance of My Making, manuscript draft (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - A Chance of My Making, manuscript draft (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - A Chance of My Making, manuscript draft (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - A Chance of My Making, manuscript draft (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - A Chance of My Making, manuscript draft (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - A Chance of My Making, manuscript draft (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - A Chance of My Making, manuscript draft (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - A Chance of My Making, manuscript draft (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - A Chance of My Making, manuscript draft (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - A Chance of My Making, manuscript draft (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - A Chance of My Making, manuscript draft (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - A Chance of My Making, manuscript draft (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - A Chance of My Making, manuscript draft (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - A Chance of My Making, manuscript draft (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - A Chance of My Making, manuscript draft (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - A Chance of My Making, manuscript draft (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - A Chance of My Making, manuscript draft (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - A Chance of My Making, synopses (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - French notes for A Chance of My Making (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Photos and illustrations for A Chance of My Making (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - "An Unexpected Welcome at Cezanne’s Hometown," manuscript (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - "Greece," Manuscript (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - "Notes on Teaching Painting," Manuscript (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Poetry, manuscripts (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Poetry, manuscripts (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Poetry, manuscripts (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Poetry, manuscripts (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - "Spain, 1965," manuscript (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - "The Invisible Fortress," manuscript drafts (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - "Evolution of Man," manuscript (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - "The Driftwood Horse," manuscript drafts (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - "Toreo de Novilladas," manuscript (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - "Creative Women," manuscript drafts (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - "The Toy Train," manuscript drafts (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - "Cat Tales"/"Mr. Annie," manuscript drafts (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - "Sketches from Life," manuscript drafts (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - "Knucklebones, Jacks, and Craps," manuscript drafts (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - "An Americanist in Paris," manuscript (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - "Round Robin Portrait," manuscript drafts (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Marsden Hartley in Maine, book (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Illustrations for Marsden Hartley in Maine (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Marsden Hartley in Maine, manuscript drafts and illustrations (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence about Marsden Hartley and Hartley manuscript, 1943-1971 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence about Marsden Hartley and Hartley manuscript, 1972-1977 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence about Marsden Hartley in Maine, 1972-1976 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Marsden Hartley, exhibits (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Manuscript fragments and notes (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Four Strings to a Note, manuscript (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous photos and documents (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Drawing, undated (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Articles by Van Meter Ames (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Poems by Vere Dargan (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - "The Illuminati," Manuscript by Charles Harvey Arnold (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Press coverage and sales of paintings (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Publicity and correspondence for exhibitions (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Publicity and correspondence for exhibitions (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Press clippings (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous articles and programs (Box 11, Folder 13)
- Series II: Correspondence and Journals
  - Correspondence about death of E.S. Ames, 1958 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence about death of E.S. Ames, 1958-1959 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence about death of E.S. Ames, undated (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous documents about E.S. Ames (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous personal and professional correspondence, 1938-1986 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Ames family correspondence, 1938-1954 and undated (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence with E.E. Cummings, July – Dec 1960, undated, Contains 3 typed letters signed, 2 typed cards signed, 1 autograph letter signed, and handwritten notes on the back of a hotel bill. (Box 12A, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence with Marion Cummings, July 1960 – Feb. 1968, Contains 14 letters with 9 envelopes, a newspaper clipping, and 2 greeting cards. One of the cards reproduces a painting by e. e. cummings. (Box 12A, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence with Marianne Moore, July – Aug. 1951 (Box 12A, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence with and about Adelaide and Henry Schade, 1938-1980 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence with and about Adelaide and Henry Schade, 1980-1981 and undated (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Publication rejection notices, 1963-1984 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Hyde Park Music Club, member lists (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Journal, 1951 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Journal, June - July 1960 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Journal, August - September 1960 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Journal, 1960 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Journal, 1960-1962 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Journal, 1962 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Journal, 1963 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Journal, 1964 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Journal, 1965 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Journal, 1967 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Journal, 1967-1968 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Journal, 1981 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Journal, 1992-1993 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Journal, undated (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Journal, undated (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Journal, undated (Box 15, Folder 7)
- Series III: Oversize Materials
  - Article on Marsden Hartley (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Press clippings and exhibition posters (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Map of Maine (Box 16, Folder 3)